Guide to the James E. Dyer Papers MS 052
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
James E. Dyer Papers
Bulk, 1970-1985
1908-2010
MS 052
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
75.0 Linear feet 102 boxes, 14 oversized boxes, scrapbooks and miscellaneous objects
James Edmund Dyer, graduate of Western Connecticut State College and politician, was born in Danbury, Connecticut, on September 20, 1946. His papers span the years 1900 to 2008, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1970 to 1990, primarily documenting his work as Mayor of Danbury, Connecticut. Information regarding his activities at Western Connecticut State College, his two terms as Trustee of the Connecticut State Colleges, and State Representative for the 110th District is also included. The collection consists of biographical materials, legislative and trustee files, citations, correspondence, fliers, greeting cards, membership cards, newsletters, news clippings, scrapbooks, petitions, photographs, posters, postcards, press releases, printed materials, proclamations, resolutions, writings and campaign materials such as bumper stickers, campaign pins, sample ballots, and mailing lists.
Dyer, James E.
Biographical/Historical note
James Edmund Dyer was born in Danbury, Connecticut, on September 20, 1946, to Thomas J. and Mary Murphy Dyer.
Dyer was first introduced to politics at the tender age of five by his politically active father who brought him along to party headquarter and door to door canvassing with him.
Dyer graduated from Norwalk Community College in 1968 with an A. S. in Business Administration and Western Connecticut State College in 1972 with a Bachelor’s degree in History. While at Western Connecticut State College, Dyer was active in student government and in yearbook committees.
Dyer entered the political arena in 1970 when Governor Dempsey appointed him to the Board of Trustees for the Connecticut State Colleges (1971-1972). He became the first undergraduate student in the state’s history to serve in that capacity. He was appointed for a second term in 1975 by Governor Ella Grasso.
During this time, Dyer was a delegate to the White House Conference on Children and served on the Education Sub-Committee, and in 1972 went to work as a congressional aide to former Congressman John S. Monagan from Connecticut’s Fifth Congressional District. Dyer was also active in community affairs serving as chairman of the Danbury Youth Commission, president of the Danbury Young Democrats, a member of the CSC Alumni Board of Directors and member of the Search Committee for a new WCSC president.
Dyer was elected to the Connecticut House of Representatives from the 110th Assembly District in 1976 and re-elected in 1978. While a member of the Connecticut House of Representatives Dyer served on the Education, Judiciary and General Law Committees, and was Chairman of the Higher Education Sub-Committee.
From 1979 to 1987 Dyer served four terms as Danbury’s Mayor. During his tenure, Dyer invested millions of dollars in infrastructure improvements, education, historic preservation and programs benefiting youth and senior citizens services. Improvements on Route 7 and widening of Interstate 84 between exits 3 and 8, as well as the Osborne Street/Garamella Boulevard connector, are among the many road projects that were initiated and completed to alleviate traffic congestion.
Also during his tenure, proposed plans for a mall on the Danbury Fairgrounds by Wilmorite, Inc., were finalized and executed creating jobs and additional revenue for the City.
In 1987 Dyer ran for a fifth term and was defeated by Joseph H. Sauer, a retired school teacher. After losing the election, Dyer joined Applied Data, Inc., in North Haven, Connecticut, as Director of Marketing and Communication. During this time Dyer also taught a night class on urban policy at New York University. In late 1988 Dyer announced he intended to re-enter the mayoral race but withdrew in March 1989 when he learned he was going to be indicted by a federal grand jury for extortion and racketeering. In February 1990, Dyer was acquitted of all charges but one, which the U. S. Court of Appeals reversed.
In 1992, Dyer joined the New Jersey School of Architecture in Newark, New Jersey, as Associate Dean. While there he taught an honors seminar and lectured on the role of the university in community design and planning.
In 1996 Dyer published his memoirs, “when the LEAVES begin to TURN” reflecting on his 50 years in Danbury.
Dyer resides in Danbury with his wife Alice and their four children: Christopher, Brendan, Whitney and Trevor. His hobbies are photography and collecting presidential letters and political Americana.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of James Edmund Dyer span the years 1900 to 2008, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1970 to 1990, and primarily document his work while Mayor of Danbury, Connecticut.
The collection is organized into three series: Personal, Western Connecticut State College, and Political and Professional. The collection is organized chronologically then alphabetically within each series and consists of biographical materials, citations, correspondence, fliers, greeting cards, membership cards, newsletters, news clippings, scrapbooks, petitions, posters, postcards, press releases, printed materials, proclamations, resolutions, writings and campaign materials such as bumper stickers, campaign pins, sample ballots and mailing lists. Series 1 contains personal items relating to Dyer’s youth, his mother and father, Mary and Thomas Dyer, his wife Alice Wenzler Dyer, and his four children: Christopher, Brendan, Whitney, and Trevor. Items include diplomas, copies of birth certificates, photographs, blue prints, certificates of appreciation, and press clippings regarding special events, such as birthdays and anniversaries, and audio and visual tapes relating to his family.
Dyer is also a collector of presidential manuscripts and political Americana. He owns one of the largest private collections of Kennedy memorabilia, which has been displayed in many cities and area schools. Series 1 also contains presidential recordings and transcripts of President John F. Kennedy’s meetings with staff and advisors on Integration of the University of Mississippi, Tax Cut Proposals, Peace Corps, Cuban Missile Crisis, and Civil Rights. Comments and correspondence regarding Dyer’s private collection can be found in this series as well as correspondence with Kennedy’s personal secretary, Evelyn Lincoln. Dyer was also a frequent speaker at the annual John F. Kennedy memorial service in Danbury as well as in area schools where he spoke on Kennedy’s life and presidency.
Series 2 contains information on Dyer while he was a student at Western Connecticut State College and Trustee on the State College Board. During his years at Wesconn Dyer became more involved in local and state politics. In 1969 Dyer ran for president of the student body and lost the election. With an unsuccessful campaign behind him, he sought and won the vice presidency in 1970. Information regarding his campaigns and elections can also be found in issues of the Echo, published by the student body of WCSC.
In 1970, Governor John Dempsey appointed Dyer to serve on the State College’s Board of Trustees becoming the first undergraduate student in the state’s history to be appointed to a major board of public education.
Dyer also served as the official yearbook photographer during his school years and for several years after graduation.
Correspondence, clippings and speeches during this time indicate Dyer’s belief that change was due on state college campuses. Dyer established and served as chairman of the Keep Tuition Down Committee, established and served as state coordinator to the Coalition Against Tuition Committee, and was a member of Vote 18 Committee.
While Trustee, Dyer held unprecedented public forums on all four campuses so students, and faculty alike, could air issues of concern. Information on the public forums is covered extensively by news clippings, speeches, and press releases during this time. Researchers should also see copies of the Echo for additional information. Dyer’s published report on the open forums is located in box 18/10.
Governor Dempsey also nominated Dyer as a delegate to the 1970 White House Conference on Children and invited to attend by President Nixon. He served on the Connecticut Planning Committee and later on the Education Sub-Committee.
Series 3 contains information on Dyer’s political and professional career. With ten years of experience in government and the political process, Dyer’s political career began in earnest in 1976 when he ran as the Democratic candidate for State Representative representing Danbury’s 110th Legislative District in the Connecticut General Assembly. He won by a two to one margin and ran for a second term in 1978 and won with over 70% of the vote. Information regarding these two elections and Dyer’s activities in local and state politics that eventually led to his nomination and election is covered in depth in the chronological news clippings within this series. A brief summary of legislation, projects, and special concerns that Dyer worked on can be found in Box 48/14 in a copy of a letter to his constituents.
Dyer served four terms as Danbury’s Mayor from 1979 to 1987. Information regarding his campaigns and mayoral duties provides insight into local political campaigning and the varied duties and issues of public office. The chronological filing of this series will give the researcher the opportunity to follow the progression of certain projects from inception to fruition. Two city development projects of interest are the Redevelopment Agency’s plans to revitalize Danbury’s central business district and the controversy surrounding the choice of developer, and the building of the Danbury Fair Mall on the Danbury Fair grounds. Both projects are covered in depth and additional information can be found in news clippings.
During 1987 the FBI conducted a two year investigation looking into allegations of municipal corruption. Fallout from the FBI probe was a factor in Dyer’s loss in the November 1987 election. In December 1988 Dyer announced his intention to recapture the mayor’s office. He withdrew in March 1989, days before his indictment by a federal grand jury on seven counts of racketeering, extortion, and tax evasion. He was acquitted on charges of extortion and racketeering but convicted of filing a false income tax return in 1986. The conviction was overturned when an appeals court said New Haven U. S. District Court Judge Jose A. Cabranes erred when instructing the jury. Also, on a legal technicality, the Second Court of Appeals dismissed the government’s appeal to overturn a federal judge’s decision to bar crucial testimony in a re-trial of Dyer on the tax charge.
The correspondence files within this series are mainly incoming from local constituents voicing their concerns on issues as well as congratulatory notes and well wishes. Pre-trial and post-trial correspondence contain letters and notes of encouragement and well wishes from friends and family, and congratulatory notes and cards upon his acquittal.
The Casework files contain incoming and outgoing correspondence from the mayor’s office regarding issues of concern from constituents as well as internal correspondence between the mayor’s office and city departments. Dyer often sent handwritten replies that are indicative of his concern regarding certain issues. Interns assigned to the Mayor’s office often researched and replied to these letters as well.
The plaques and certificates which were awarded Dyer by different organizations in recognition of his contributions and services to various fields indicate the diverse range of activities in which he was involved.
Arrangement note
Three series, chronologically and alphabetically:
Series I: Personal and Family Papers Series II: WestConn Materials Series III: Political and Professional Career
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions except:
Box 1/10-12, House ID with Social Security Number Box 19/1-6, Campus Search Committee Box 19/7, Correspondence re Stephen Feldman Box 51/1-2, Personnel Notes & Biographies Box 83/8-10, NYU Class, Final Papers & Grade Book
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by James E. Dyer over a period of six months during 2010.
City of Danbury. Office of the Mayor..; Connecticut. General Assembly. House of Representatives..; Dyer, Mary; Dyer, Thomas J.; Feldman, Stephen.; Haas, Ruth A., 1903-1986.; Western Connecticut State College -- History.; Audiotapes.; Biographical files; Bumper stickers; Buttons (information artifacts); Campaign posters; City planning -- Connecticut -- Danbury; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Danbury (Conn.); Danbury (Conn.) -- Church History.; Danbury (Conn.) -- Economic conditions; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Danbury (Conn.) -- Redevelopment Agency; Danbury Tricentennial; Fliers (printed matter); Greeting cards; Land use, Urban.; Mailing lists; Membership cards; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Petitions; Photographs.; Political campaigns; Political posters; Postcards; Posters; Proclamations; Resolutions (administrative records); Scrapbooks.; Speeches.; Universities and Colleges -- Western Connecticut State University.; Urban policy; Videotapes.; Western Connecticut State University - History
- Series I: Personal and Family Papers, RG6.xx___x
  - Subseries A: James E. Dyer Materials, RG6.xx___x
    - "Pen used to sign 'Merson Agreement' December 12th 1912" (ink pen) (Box 22)
    - Silhouettes of JD by Andre Engel (3 items), 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - An Open Letter of a Chicago Waiter to Winston Churchill by Tadeusz Kwasniewski (Author's Gift, Mar. 27, 1951) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - First business card, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Grammar School Papers, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - A Pictorial Review of the Danbury and Northern Fairfield County Flood of Oct. 15-16, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ABC TV's Shock Club membership card, ca.1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Crayon drawing of a fox hunt, undated (Box OS 11)
    - Correspondence (ASL William A. Purtell, Antoni Sadlak, Prescott Bush, Albert Morano and Thomas J. Dodd), 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John S. Monagan (includes House ID with SS#) Closed, 1958-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    - John S. Monagan Campaign Memorabilia, 1960-1982 (Box OS 5)
    - Danbury High School, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - "The Desperate Hours, A Play" Script by Joseph Hayes (JD age 12), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "The Desperate Hours, A Play" (poster), 1959 (Box OS 11)
    - Dyer Research Development (Science experiments: diary, notes, and photographs), 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hayestown Memories, Hayestown Avenue School Yearbook, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Memorabilia, 1959-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Brass paperweight with tall ship scrimshaw, undated (Box 25)
    - Key Ring "Martin's Complete Outfitters for Men & Boys", undated (Box 25)
    - Megaphone, Danbury High School Newspaper, November 1, 1960; April 1962; June and November 1975, 1960-1975 (Box OS 11)
    - Danbury High School clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Danbury High School papers, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
    - U. S. Senate Passes Signed by Edward M.Kennedy, Thomas J.Dodd, Abe Ribicoff, and U. S. House of Representatives Pass (6 passes), 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Charcoal portrait of James Dyer signed by Barrows (16x20 framed), 1962 (Box OS 6)
    - Driver licenses, 1962-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Scott Fanton Museum, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Trip With Dad" (diary), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Cars/Corvette, 1963-1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Cars/Corvette License Plate "VETTE - 1", 1963-1987 (Box 25)
    - National Thespian Society Membership Card, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - National Thespian Society Recognition (framed), 1963 (Box 25)
    - America goes to the polls; highlights of the presidential campaigns, 1789-1964: A tribute to America's political freedom by The Travelers Insurance Companies. Third edition (Box 90)
    - Danbury High School Diploma and Program, June 23, 1964, w/cover and admission tickets (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Danbury High School, Flynn Campaign, June 1964 (Includes three b/w photographs of JD/James Flynn) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Carrier's Route Book, Danbury News-Times, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Selective Service System Notice of Classification Cards, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Napoleon's March to Moscow, War of 1812 ( One 15x22 Poster), ca.1965 (Box OS 11)
    - Blue Beats pin, news release and entry passes, 1964-1965 (Box 22)
    - Clippings, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - College ID cards (New Haven College & Norwalk Community College), 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence (outgoing), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Danbury City Park and Danbury Fish & Game Ass'n Pins, 1965-1980 (Box 22)
    - Membership Cards (Political Collectors Clubs), 1966-1991 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 100 Years in Danbury, 1866-1966 by The Union Savings Bank of Danbury (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - American Political Items Collectors National and Chapter Conventions name tags/ribbons, pins (22 items), 1967 (Box 22)
    - Application for admission as an elector in the Town of Danbury, Oct. 14, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Application for Enrollment in the Democratic Party, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - com collegiate, Norwalk Community College Student News, March 6, 1967, and January 12, 1968, 1967-1968 (Box OS 11)
    - Norwalk Community College Papers, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - Norwalk Community College Papers, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Waldorf-Astoria Food and Beverage Menu and Post Card, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Norwalk Community College Diploma, June 5, 1968 (w/cover) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Travel (Boston, NYC, DC, Nevada, California, North Dakota), 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - JD Biographical Information, 1970-1984 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
    - WCSC Diploma, January 23, 1972 (w/cover) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - City of Danbury Voter Identification Card, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Connecticut Attached: A British Viewpoint, Tryon's Raid on Danbury by Robert McDevitt, 1974, 1964-1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Personal (incoming) ALS Ella Grasso, 1974-1988 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Charles Ives Centennial Concert with Leonard Bernstein and Michael Tilson Thomas (program and ticket stub), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Danbury Town Guide, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1977-1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Telescopic View Card, Queen Elizabeth's Silver Jubilee, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - John Lennon, 1980-2005 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Plot Plan, Lot 15 - Section 'A' Map No.6, Aunt Hack Ridge Estates, Inc., 1981 (Box OS 11)
    - Distinguished Alumnus Achievement Award from Norwalk Community College, 1981 (Box 26)
    - Aunt Hack Road, Lot 15, Contract Information, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence (incoming) ALS Wm.O'Neill, Toby Moffett, Wm. R. Ratchord, Lowell Weicker, Jr., Joseph Lieberman, Chris Dodd, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
    - Omaha Beach 1944-1984 Remembrance (poster) (Box OS 11)
    - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - JD/AW Wedding Plans, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mayor's Proclamation: Alice Wenzler has accepted the Mayor's commitment of marriage, 1985 (Box OS 3)
    - Blessing from John Paul II to James Dyer and Family (framed), 1985 (Box 26)
    - "MR. & MRS. JAMES E. DYER" Name Plate, ca.1985 (Box 22)
    - Stationery (note card), ca.1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "21" Club; Correspondence, Clippings, Pamphlets, 1985-1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Statue of Liberty Centennial, 1886-1986 Pin (Box 92)
    - Westconnnopoly 1986 Edition (custom board game) (Box OS 8)
    - Dyer family menus for holidays and special events, 1986-2009 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Family Memorabilia, 1986-2009 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence (incoming), 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence (incoming), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence (mainly incoming) ALS Stephen Feldman, John Rowland, Richard Blumenthal, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 4-8)
    - Correspondence (mainly incoming), 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
    - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Brendan's Baptism Invitation, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence (incoming/outgoing), 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Memorial Cards "In Loving Memory" Cards, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - A Mild Shout: Anti-War Protest at WCSC, 1967-1969 by Colleen Blair, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Thanks and Appreciation from the Holly's Folly Cast and Crew (Plaque), 1994 (Box 26)
    - when the LEAVES begin to TURN (28x36 promotional poster on foam core), 1996 (Item 32)
    - when the LEAVES begin to TURN (11x16 promotional poster and clipping), 1996 (Box OS 11)
    - when the LEAVES begin to TURN (Book), 1996 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Dyer-Svege Funeral, Clippings and Notes, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mayor's Race 2007, 2000-2007 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
    - 9/11 Emails, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 2002-2009 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Gettysburg Memorabilia, 2005-2008 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 2005-2009 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence (incoming from children attending Mill Ridge Primary School), 2006 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Mill Plain Traffic Notes and Clippings, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subseries B: Thomas Dyer (Father) Materials, RG6.xx___x
    - City Court receipts for expenses incurred transporting prisoners to jail and other expenses, 1900-1909 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Thomas Dyer: WWI: Photographs and Enlistment Record (Copies), 1915-1918 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Thomas Dyer: K of C McGivney Council, Oct.1916; and, Elks Minstrels Nov.3-4, 1916, Photographs (photocopies) (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - WWI Diary, Soldier Unknown (copy), ca.1918 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Knights of Columbus, McGivney Council 29, Bulding Committee, Danbury, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Small booklet with "Mallory Hats" on cover. Contains Pumkin Pie Recipe, ca.1920 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Danbury Creamery, Inc." Milk Bottle, ca.1920 (Box 25)
    - Danbury and Our Boys in the World War by Anna Hornik. Note: Thomas J. Dyer was a WWI combat veteran. He served on the Common Council for 11 years. He organized the Memorial Day Parade and other verteran's events for 30 years. Includes copies of TJD's Honorable Discharge paper and copies of four WW I photos identifying TJD., 1923 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company Certificate, 1928-1934 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Memorabilia, 1951- 1975 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Personal Papers (ALS Lowell Weicker, Ella Grasso, W. A. O'Neill, Chris Dodd, Ron Sarasin, Bill Ratchford), 1951-1985 (Box 8, Folder 10-12)
    - Veterans of World War I, 8th and 10th National Convention and Grand Reunion Booklets, 1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Clippings, 1957-1977 (Box 8, Folder 14-18)
    - Proclamations, Resolutions, Official Citations, Certificates (9), 1961-1994 (Box OS 5)
    - Thomas Dyer: Certified Copy of Birth Record (laminated), and Social Security Card, 1966-1985 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Election Memorabilia, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Campaign Material, 1967-1977 (Box OS 13)
    - Memorial Day Parade, May 30, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous Political Memorabilia, 1969-1977 (Box 8, Folder 22-23)
    - Memorial Day Services, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 24)